NATHAN A. COLLMAN

McMaster University
Dept. of Computing and Software
1280 Main Street West, Hamilton, Ontario, Canada, L8S 4K1
collmana@mcmaster.ca

PROFILE

Passionate, meticulous, goal oriented graduate student with strong technical, analytical, and research skills. Versed in many computing paradigms, with a penchant for interface design and web technologies. Has experience working in multicultural societies. Excels both as a team leader and a team member. Possesses excellent writing and communication skills in English and Japanese.

EDUCATION

MCMASTER UNIVERSITY

Hamilton, Canada - M.A.Sc. Software Engineering

Sept 2012 - (May 2014)

Received Graduate Scholarship worth CAD \$6000. Member of the G-ScalE (Gaming Scalability Environment) lab. Thesis deals with the specification of a domain specific language describing the Bullet Hell game genre, and the development of a code generator to generate browser-based games implementing the aforementioned DSL.

UNIVERSITY OF THE WEST INDIES MONA CAMPUS

Kingston, Jamaica - B.Sc. Computer Science, First Class Honours

Jul 2010

Received Faculty of Computer Science Award given to the student with the best academic performance over the degree period. Awarded JAM \$75,000 merit-based Stanley Grieg Memorial Scholarship. Awarded University merit-based awards for excellence.

EXPERIENCE

MCMASTER UNIVERSITY

CS2S03 Teaching Assistant, Hamilton, Canada Sept 2012/13 - Dec 2012/13 Served as TA for CS2S03, Principles of Programming. designed to provide a comprehensive coverage of the fundamental programming concepts. Responsibilities:

- I. Hold bi-weekly office hours to facilitate the answering of questions held by students regarding course material and assignments.
- II. Oversee and invigilate exam proceedings.
- III. Provide input to and mark student assignments, midterms and final exams.

JAPANESE EXCHANGE AND TEACHING PROGRAMME (JET)

English Teacher, Koriyama, Sendai, Japan

Jun 2010 - Jun 2012

Selected as cultural liaison for one of Japan's leading cultural exchange programmes, administered by Japan's Ministry of Foreign Affairs in cooperation with local governments.

Responsibilities:

- I. Serve as only non-Japanese member on 6-person team to evaluate ϑ reorganize English language program; developed more than 100 new text ϑ audio assets.
- II. Create interactive English language boards to facilitate student learning.
- III. Serve as an ambassador for Jamaica sharing Jamaican culture with the Japanese.

Achievements:

- I. Advised city officials on new technology and methods to update the online community for English teachers in Sendai.
- II. Taught English & foreign culture (sport, arts) to over 800 Japanese school students from ages 5-15.
- III. Conceptualized, presented and coordinated lectures on teaching methods to Sendai teachers.
- IV. Coached 1st place student in Miyagi Prefecture's Junior High School English Speech Contest.

2010 YOUNG CORE LEADERS OF CIVIL SOCIETY GROUPS DEVELOPMENT PROGRAM

Interpreter, Sendai, Japan

Feb 2011

1st Annual Conference focusing on the integration of people with disabilities into the wider society.

Responsibilities:

- I. Form a group of only 4 interpreters overseeing over 100 panelists and guests respectively.
- II. Organise and oversee open discussion among panelists and guests.

III. Convey complex ideas in Japanese to English and vice versa to nonnative Japanese and English speakers respectively.

GYC (GLOBAL YOUTH CONNECTION)

Web Developer, Kingston, Jamaica

Aug 2009 - Jul 2010

A micro-finance initiative that empowers youth through web and mobile technologies.

Responsibilities:

I. Conceptualize, design, develop, test, launch and maintain GYC website and other technologies.

Achievements:

- I. Collaborated with a team of five on the creation of an open source mobile communication system.
- II. Oversaw development of a collaborative project management solution for geographically separated members.

CYBERMASTER WEB DEVELOPMENT

Founder and Lead Programmer, Kingston, Jamaica Apr 2008 - Jul 2010 Founded registered Web development company during university. Responsibilities:

- I. Conceptualize, design, develop, test, launch and maintain web sites.
- II. Direct and review discourse between end-users and clients.

Achievements:

I. Established the re-branding of 2 Jamaican organisations.

UNIVERSITY OF THE WEST INDIES MONA

Lab & Teaching Assistant, Kingston, Jamaica
Sept 2008 - Jul 2010
Served as a computer lab assistant and teaching assistant for CS11A & CS11B (Introduction to Computer Science I and II) and CS34W (Web Design and Programming II).

Responsibilities:

- I. Administration and grading of labs and submitted work.
- II. Supplement instruction given in lectures outside of the class environment.
- III. Assist students in the identifying of bugs and possible solutions

SKILLS Technical:

Most comfortable with: JavaScript/JS Libraries (jQuery, Moo-tools & Prototype), Python, HTML5, CSS3 (SASS & Stylus), Haskell, Java, PHP, BackboneJS, Brunch.io, JSON, XML, Google and Yahoo APIs.

Some experience with: NodeJS, Scala, Scheme, C++, Objective C, Ruby on Rails, SQL (MySQL, SQLite, ORACLE), noSQL(MongoDB), AGILE approaches. (SCRUM)

Knowledge of Mac OS X, Microsoft Windows and Linux. Experience with Adobe Creative Suite, Pixelmator, GIMP, Eclipse IDE, Xcode, Dashcode and Sublime Text 3 (editor of choice), Bash scripting and Git/SVN.

Non-Technical:

- I. Excellent writing, presentation and communication skills.
- II. Excels as both a team player and in positions of leadership.
- III. Served as the first foreign assistant football coach of Kohriyama Junior High School
- IV. Arsenal supporter and a mean FIFA 14 player.
- V. An accomplished home-baker.

Languages: Proficient in Japanese (Japanese Language Proficiency Test Certification Level I in July 2012).

Volunteer:

- I. Volunteered for Samaritans Purse (2011), cleaning and restoring peoples homes after the Great East Japan Earthquake.
- II. Acted as mentor for Butterfly Kids Programme (2010-2011) interacting with children disaster victims through English.
- III. Sunshine Kids Programme (2010) weekend teacher for elementary school children.
- IV. Acted as Stage Manager and Performer at Tohoku Smile (2011) relief concert for disaster victims of the Great East Japan Earthquake.